<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ruby on ilkka.io</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/ruby/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ruby on ilkka.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2015 Ilkka Laukkanen. &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Some rights reserved&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2011 22:19:50 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/ruby/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Jitsu is a meta build system for Ninja</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2011/02/13/jitsu-is-a-meta-build-system-for-ninja/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2011 22:19:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2011/02/13/jitsu-is-a-meta-build-system-for-ninja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while back I hit upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/martine/ninja&#34;&gt;Ninja&lt;/a&gt;, a very fast
and very simple build system that is apparently used for building
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chromium.org/&#34;&gt;Chromium&lt;/a&gt;. Can&amp;rsquo;t remember where I first heard of
it, might&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; or just
somebody&amp;rsquo;s tweet, but having been interested in build systems for years, at
least since setting up Linux builds from scratch for a big piece of software
while working on my M.Sc. thesis, I immediately started playing around with
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ninja is indeed fast, but by design the buildfiles are hard to write. Ninja
sources include a patch to &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/gyp&#34;&gt;Gyp&lt;/a&gt;, a higher-level
build system also somehow (not sure how exactly) related to Chromium, but the
support wasn&amp;rsquo;t very complete, and somehow I just didn&amp;rsquo;t find Gyp appealing. I
therefore did what anyone in my circumstances would&amp;rsquo;ve done, and started
writing a &amp;ldquo;meta build system&amp;rdquo; myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ilkka/jitsu&#34;&gt;Jitsu&lt;/a&gt;, and since I really like
Ruby, that&amp;rsquo;s what I wrote it in. It&amp;rsquo;s at version 0.1.2 now and available from
rubygems.org, and as of now it can build (or rather, generate ninja buildfiles
for) C++ binaries and static libraries. Builds are specified as &lt;code&gt;build.jitsu&lt;/code&gt;
files in YAML format, which the tool processes into &lt;code&gt;build.ninja&lt;/code&gt; files that
can then be used by Ninja. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep trying to use it in my own projects so
hopefully it&amp;rsquo;ll keep on improving from here on out. Let&amp;rsquo;s see where it will
go, I haven&amp;rsquo;t really delineated the scope yet, to e.g. just doing C++ builds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, install the gem, maybe &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ilkka/jitsu&#34;&gt;grab the
source&lt;/a&gt; and give it a spin. Let me know what
you think. Also see &lt;a href=&#34;http://ilkka.github.com/jitsu&#34;&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teach Vim about Gemfiles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2011/02/03/teach-vim-about-gemfiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2011 18:27:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2011/02/03/teach-vim-about-gemfiles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By default, the excellent Vim editor doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what the filetype of
Gemfiles is (it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;ruby&lt;/code&gt;, of course). I&amp;rsquo;ve been sprinkling Vim modelines in
mine for ages, but just now as I was hacking at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ilkka/ticgit&#34;&gt;my clone of
ticgit&lt;/a&gt;, I realized that it makes no sense to
sprinkle these onto other people&amp;rsquo;s code so liberally when I could just teach
Vim to Do The Right Thing.  So, I promptly added the following
autocommand into my &lt;code&gt;vimrc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #272822&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #75715e&#34;&gt;&amp;quot; I put my autocommands in a block like this&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #f8f8f2&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;exists&lt;span style=&#34;color: #f8f8f2&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;autocommandsLoaded&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #f8f8f2&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span style=&#34;color: #66d9ef&#34;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; autocommandsLoaded &lt;span style=&#34;color: #f8f8f2&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
  ...
  autocmd &lt;span style=&#34;color: #f8f8f2&#34;&gt;BufNewFile,BufRead&lt;/span&gt; Gemfile &lt;span style=&#34;color: #66d9ef&#34;&gt;setlocal&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #66d9ef&#34;&gt;filetype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #f8f8f2&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #66d9ef&#34;&gt;ruby&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #66d9ef&#34;&gt;endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all &lt;code&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt;s are opened in ruby mode and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to annoy other
people with my editor-specific modelines any more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fix Outlook Quoting Style</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2011/01/31/fix-outlook-quoting-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2011/01/31/fix-outlook-quoting-style/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like many others before and after myself, I find myself having to use MS
Outlook in my daily work. Also like many, I loathe its style of quoting email
messages. Fortunately I use Exchange&amp;rsquo;s rather surprisingly good (as of the
2007 version) OWA web client, so with Firefox&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/its-all-text/&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s All
Text&lt;/a&gt; extension,
Vim and some Ruby code, I can fix quoting in messages I&amp;rsquo;m replying to easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Googling for a ready-made solution I came across &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mail-archive.com/gnhlug@zk3.dec.com/msg13395.html&#34;&gt;a post to gnhlug&amp;rsquo;s mailing
list&lt;/a&gt; that had a
Perl solution, albeit one supporting only English and only older Exchange
versions, but it gave me the spark I needed to write my own implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas (as far as I can tell) the original author wanted to correct the
quoting style of all the participants in the conversation, I thought that was
unnecessarily disruptive and only opted to correctly quote the message I would
be replying to. The usage scenario then is something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In OWA, choose to reply to a message. Horribly quoted message text appears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use It&amp;rsquo;s All Text or some other similar tool to open message text in a
reasonably smart editor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Filter entire message text through this script. E.g. in Vim type
&lt;code&gt;:%!path-to-script.rb&lt;/code&gt;, after making the script executable of course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Replace original mesage text with output of filter. If using It&amp;rsquo;s All Text,
just type &lt;code&gt;:wq&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presto! Correctly quoted message. You might have to move your sig, though.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s how to use it, now here&amp;rsquo;s the script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script
src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/803961.js?file=fix-outlook-quoting.rb&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rakefile for Jekyll site management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/12/08/rakefile-for-jekyll-site-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 17:00:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/12/08/rakefile-for-jekyll-site-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Previously I&amp;rsquo;ve used a bunch of scripts for managing post creation and site
compilation tasks, but recently I decided to move over to Rake. The whole
Rakefile as-it-stands is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ilkka/ilkka.github.com/tree/source&#34;&gt;in the
repo&lt;/a&gt;, naturally, but
here&amp;rsquo;s a couple of bits I&amp;rsquo;m finding useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt; task set up that runs compass, jekyll, and &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt;s
and &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;es the result. The compass and jekyll bits are simple &lt;code&gt;sh&lt;/code&gt;
steps, but the rest is a bit more involved. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with post creation
though, in the spirit of the real workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ruby&#34;&gt;
namespace &#34;post&#34; do
  desc &#34;Given a title as an argument, create a new post file&#34;
  task :new, [:title] do |t, args|
    now = DateTime::now().to_date()
    filename = &#34;#{now.strftime}-#{args.title.gsub(/\s/, &#39;_&#39;).downcase}.markdown&#34;
    path = File.join(&#34;_posts&#34;, filename)
    if File.exist? path; raise RuntimeError.new(&#34;Won&#39;t clobber #{path}&#34;); end
    File.open(path, &#39;w&#39;) do |file|
      file.write &lt;&lt;-EOS
---
layout: post
title: #{args.title}
---

Content goes here
EOS
    end
    puts &#34;Now open #{path} in an editor.&#34;
  end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above listing is the new post creation task, and the entirety of the
&lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt; namespace currently, as it happens. It takes the post title as an
argument, and uses that and the current date to generate a filename. At the
moment it just replaces whitespace with underscores, but it might be good to
do more escaping to ensure a good filename. Then the task writes a post
template into the file and prints the filename so it&amp;rsquo;s easy to launch an
editor for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure good clean commits of the site I clean the &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory before
compilation, i.e. delete all files except for any dotfiles, so as not to
destroy the &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt; dir in there. I use a helper method to get a list of all
the files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ruby&#34;&gt;
def site_files
  FileList[&#39;_site/**/*&#39;].find_all {|f| File.file? f}
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file list is then used in the &lt;code&gt;clean&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;commit&lt;/code&gt; tasks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ruby&#34;&gt;
desc &#34;Clean generated site files&#34;
task :clean do
  FileUtils.rm site_files
end

desc &#34;Commit compiled site to Git&#34;
task :commit do
  g = Git.open(&#39;_site&#39;)
  g.add site_files.map {|f| f.gsub(/^_site\//, &#39;&#39;)}
  g.commit &#34;Regenerated&#34;
end

desc &#34;Push committed site to GitHub&#34;
task :push do
  g = Git.open(&#39;_site&#39;)
  g.push
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;clean&lt;/code&gt; task is simple because one can use the filelist directly, but when
committing, the &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; dir bit has to be dropped from the filenames with a
simple &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;gsub&lt;/code&gt; combo. I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/schacon&#34;&gt;Scott
Chacon&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/schacon/ruby-git&#34;&gt;ruby-git
gem&lt;/a&gt; to perform git operations on the
repo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s pretty much it for the moment. I might expand the post management
features a bit at some point though, but since most of that is no simpler via
Rake than through shell commands and an editor, it remains to be seen what
those new features might be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jekyll tag cloud</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/11/21/jekyll-tag-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 23:11:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/11/21/jekyll-tag-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/11/20/hosting-a-jekyll-blog-with-extensions-on-github&#34;&gt;gotten archives
working&lt;/a&gt;
nicely, I decided to next tackle the task of creating a tag cloud for
my blog. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Template-Data&#34;&gt;Jekyll
docs&lt;/a&gt; are,
sadly, a bit ambiguous on how exactly to get at all the available
categories, for example, but as with my archive plugin, I decided to
go ahead and try out stuff until something workable emerged. With
archive pages, all that needed to be done was to write a generator
plugin to create more pages. With tags, however, I want to do
more. Specifically, I want to generate a tag cloud into my layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Googling a bit I came across &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/364416&#34;&gt;a gist&lt;/a&gt;
where tag cloud generation was done in the &lt;code&gt;Rakefile&lt;/code&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want
to clutter my (as-of-then-nonexistant) &lt;code&gt;Rakefile&lt;/code&gt; with stuff like
this, and instead thought that the logical place to put this code is
in a plugin. I decided to implement the same basic idea though, where
the tag links go in &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;s that get dynamically styled with
different font sizes. Here&amp;rsquo;s the source of my new tag plugin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/710577.js?file=tag_cloud_tag.rb&#34;&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plugin class inherits from &lt;code&gt;Liquid::Tag&lt;/code&gt; and has just one method
apart from the constructor, &lt;code&gt;render&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;context&lt;/code&gt; parameter to
&lt;code&gt;render&lt;/code&gt; includes whatever data would be accessible in the template
via the &lt;code&gt;registers&lt;/code&gt; hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I must take a moment to vent a very tiny bit at Jekyll: why
and/or how is it that while the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Shopify/liquid/wiki/Liquid-for-Designers&#34;&gt;Liquid docs clearly state that only
tags in double curly brackets may resolve to
text&lt;/a&gt;,
tags defined in Jekyll tag plugins &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be put in brackets +
percent signs? Illogical, and it bit me on the ass more than once
as I was writing my plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;render&lt;/code&gt; method gets all the tags in all the articles from
&lt;code&gt;context.registers[:site].tags&lt;/code&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s a hash keyed on the tags as
strings, and the values are lists of articles that have that tag. The
&lt;code&gt;inject&lt;/code&gt; on the next lines calculates the average length of the
article arrays. Next, I just iterate over all the tags once more, and
this time use the average to calculate a weight for every
tag. Finally, I output HTML for each tag, with a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; that gets
its &lt;code&gt;font-size&lt;/code&gt; set dynamically to a percentage based on the
weight. Finally the tag is registered with Liquid and it&amp;rsquo;s ready to
use&amp;hellip; provided you remember to use the brackets-plus-percent signs
markup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tag page class and the associated generator are very similar to
the archive plugin, so I&amp;rsquo;m just going to direct you to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/710577&#34;&gt;gist with
the source code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting a Jekyll blog with extensions on GitHub</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/11/20/hosting-a-jekyll-blog-with-extensions-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 20:39:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2010/11/20/hosting-a-jekyll-blog-with-extensions-on-github/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Really there&amp;rsquo;s nothing about this article that is true any more.
I&amp;rsquo;m now running &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve finally gone and done it, it seems, and started a blog that&amp;rsquo;s
more focused than my previous attempts at Internet wordsmithery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, wait, actually this blog is &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; focused, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ilkkalaukkanen.blogspot.com&#34;&gt;previous
one&lt;/a&gt; tried to be about my
photography hobby. From the top, then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve finally gone and&amp;hellip; crud. Let&amp;rsquo;s not write one more of &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt;
posts. You know the ones. The beef here is that this is my blog, it&amp;rsquo;s
about stuff, you can find it at &lt;a href=&#34;http://ilkka.github.io&#34;&gt;http://ilkka.github.io&lt;/a&gt;, and I had
some fun with &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; while making it. If you
want to use Jekyll too, and especially want to use Jekyll &lt;code&gt;_plugins&lt;/code&gt;
together with GitHub pages, or just have a few minutes to waste with
nothing good on the youtubes, read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to talk about basic Jekyll usage since you can read all
about that elsewhere (like on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki&#34;&gt;Jekyll GitHub
wiki&lt;/a&gt;), and if you happen to
care about things like this I probably don&amp;rsquo;t have to go into detail
about the reasons why I chose it, either: the content is statically
generated from Liquid templates and a bunch of Markdown or Textile
files or even HTML, so all one needs for hosting is a web server,
everything is stored safely in git, clean and simple etc. etc. GitHub
pages is a pretty ideal hosting choice since it automagically
jekyllifies your pages &amp;ndash; which we&amp;rsquo;ll see is sometimes not so good &amp;ndash;
and is just generally totally sweet, so let&amp;rsquo;s not go there either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-revolution-will-be-archived:c2df341ce8c1080f73ca15b658053c8d&#34;&gt;The Revolution will be archived&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So. I did some Jekyll testing and saw that it was Good, but I found
that it lacked something I wanted for my site, namely archive
pages. After messing around a bit with the Liquid template language, I
came to the conclusion that it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t cut it alone and that I needed some
custom site-specific code in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Plugins&#34;&gt;Jekyll
plugins&lt;/a&gt; to get what I
wanted. The plugin mechanism in Jekyll allows one to put ruby code
along with the post sources, layouts and other stuff and have it be
executed when Jekyll runs. Ominous!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interest of coherent narrative, I&amp;rsquo;m going to totally ignore how
things actually went down and try to tell it the way they should&amp;rsquo;ve,
and the first milestone on that journey is the creation of a new page
class in Jekyll. The &lt;code&gt;ArchivePage&lt;/code&gt; class&amp;rsquo; source is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/707020.js?file=archivepage.rb&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of &lt;code&gt;ArchivePage&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s methods and ideas are copied from Jekyll&amp;rsquo;s own
&lt;code&gt;Page&lt;/code&gt; class. It mixes in &lt;code&gt;Convertible&lt;/code&gt;, therefore it can be laid out
and converted like any other page. What it does not do is read its
content from a file, instead the content is initialized in the
constructor. I know, I know, suboptimal and I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; coming up with a
better solution but this is not the point. &lt;code&gt;ArchivePage&lt;/code&gt; relies on
being provided with a ready-made list of &lt;code&gt;posts&lt;/code&gt;, and also, again
rather crudely, on a &lt;code&gt;month&lt;/code&gt; parameter that&amp;rsquo;s actually a string of the
format &amp;ldquo;YYYY/MM&amp;rdquo;, like in post URLs, and that will be in fact used as
part of an URL, which you see if you look at the &lt;code&gt;url&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;ext&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;basename&lt;/code&gt; are quite self-explanatory, but the &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt;
hash is what determines the layout and makes the posts available to
the template code in &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt;. Anything that could be set in a page&amp;rsquo;s
YAML front matter can be set here. I set the &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; of the page to be
&amp;ldquo;archive&amp;rdquo; so that I can identify these pages later as I&amp;rsquo;m iterating
&lt;code&gt;site.pages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;render&lt;/code&gt; method is what the site uses to render pages into their
final form, ready to be written to the destination. The layouts and
sitewide data are passed to it as &lt;code&gt;layouts&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;site_payload&lt;/code&gt;, and it
combines its own data with &lt;code&gt;site_payload&lt;/code&gt; and passes all that to the
&lt;code&gt;Convertible&lt;/code&gt; method &lt;code&gt;do_layout&lt;/code&gt; that does the actual converter
selection according to source format, template parsing, rendering and
so on. It uses the &lt;code&gt;to_liquid&lt;/code&gt; method which is really just a leftover
from &lt;code&gt;Page&lt;/code&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if it could be just folded into either the
constructor or &lt;code&gt;render&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;write&lt;/code&gt; is just more slightly modified copypasta from &lt;code&gt;Page&lt;/code&gt;: figure
out the destination file path into &lt;code&gt;dest&lt;/code&gt;, create the directory path
there (in two steps that could probably be combined), open a &lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt;
for writing and dump the &lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;render&lt;/code&gt; into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;talkin-bout-my-generation:c2df341ce8c1080f73ca15b658053c8d&#34;&gt;Talkin&amp;rsquo; bout my generation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;code&gt;ArchivePage&lt;/code&gt; class in a nutshell, but that alone won&amp;rsquo;t do
much: there has to a plugin class too, namely a &lt;code&gt;Generator&lt;/code&gt; subclass:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/707909.js?file=archivegenerator.rb&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Generator&lt;/code&gt; plugins have a single method for an interface,
&lt;code&gt;generate&lt;/code&gt;. It takes the &lt;code&gt;site&lt;/code&gt; as parameter, and from there one can
do pretty much what one wants. Here I go through all posts in
&lt;code&gt;collate_by_month&lt;/code&gt;, where build a hash of lists of posts keyed on the
year and month they were created. Then I simply create an
&lt;code&gt;ArchivePage&lt;/code&gt; instance for every month and, crucially, add the pages
into &lt;code&gt;site.pages&lt;/code&gt; so that I can later access them in my template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have the archive pages for all my months stored neatly with all
my other pages. All I have to do now is make them accessible. To that
end I wrote some template code, the results of which you can see down
at the bottom of this page and others, and the code looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/708018.js?file=archivelinks.html&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bit is not too elegant either, but it gets the job done and works
reasonably well &amp;ndash; which is easy to say given the single-digit post
counts I&amp;rsquo;ve tested. All it does is iterate over the whole &lt;code&gt;site.pages&lt;/code&gt;
list and pick out the pages that have a &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; value of &amp;ldquo;archive&amp;rdquo;,
which the &lt;code&gt;ArchivePage&lt;/code&gt; instances have. Presto, instant archive pages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach leads to a problem that I hinted at in the beginning
though: naturally GitHub doesn&amp;rsquo;t want random people (even if they all
are brilliant hackers) running their code on GitHub&amp;rsquo;s servers, so
Jekyll plugins don&amp;rsquo;t work when GitHub regenerates the
pages. Unfortunately I only found this out at this point, and I
already had some development history in my pages&amp;rsquo; repository&amp;rsquo;s master
branch which I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to throw away. Also I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to find
hosting elsewhere, and really didn&amp;rsquo;t want separate repos for the
source and the content, so I found myself with two problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a good workflow for writing, generating and uploading, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a good way to host both the Jekyll source and the generated site in one repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these actually kind of tie together, since the way Jekyll
normally works, meaning with the out-of-the box configuration, is to
generate the site in the &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; folder under the root of the source
tree. Now, if I want to not have to maintain two repos, I must host
the sources to this blog in the &lt;code&gt;ilkka.github.com&lt;/code&gt; repo alongside the
generated site. However, the generated site needs to be in the master
branch, and it needs to start at the root of the tree, meaning the
main &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file needs to be in the root directory, not in
e.g. &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;branching-out:c2df341ce8c1080f73ca15b658053c8d&#34;&gt;Branching out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I came up with to solve this is to use two branches: &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;
is for the generated site, since that&amp;rsquo;s what GitHub pages wants, and
I&amp;rsquo;ll create a second branch called &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; to keep the sources
in. Then I&amp;rsquo;ll add the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch as a submodule of the &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt;
branch so that it shows up as the &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; directory. This allows me to
have both branches essentially checked out at the same time, which
makes updating a breeze even if it means using twice the disk space
locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I need to do is move the sources out of &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; and
into &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to lose the history though, so I&amp;rsquo;ll have
to rename the branch, and I also don&amp;rsquo;t want the branches to share a
root &amp;ndash; there&amp;rsquo;s no commonality there &amp;ndash; so I want a pristine &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;
branch. Happily this is easy with Git. First I rename the old branch
locally:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;
git branch -m master source
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This only renames the local branch though: I still have to rename the
remote branch in GitHub, which I&amp;rsquo;ll do later. Now I create a pristine
new &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;, which is well documented in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://book.git-scm.com/5_creating_new_empty_branches.html&#34;&gt;Git Community
Book&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;
git symbolic-ref HEAD refs/heads/master
rm .git/index
git clean -fdx
touch index.html
git add your files
git commit -m &#39;Blank new master branch&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I cannot just do a normal push with this new &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch
because the master in GitHub is unrelated and cannot be merged. What I
&lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do is borrow a page from George Lucas&amp;rsquo; book and force-push:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;
git push --force origin master
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will essentially clobber the remote repo and is really not
recommended on a published repo, but in my case I think it&amp;rsquo;s pretty
unlikely that anybody else has cloned it yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all that remains is to push the &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; branch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;
git push origin source:source
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also done but not detailed here is that &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; was set to follow
&lt;code&gt;origin/master&lt;/code&gt; so I actually had to recreate it locally and set it to
follow &lt;code&gt;origin/source&lt;/code&gt;. Then I checked out &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; and added the
submodule, using my private URL so that I could commit changes to the
generated site easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;
git checkout source
git submodule add git@github.com:ilkka/ilkka.github.com.git _site
git commit -m &#34;Added site as submodule&#34;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now whenever I run Jekyll, or as I normally do, namely have &lt;code&gt;compass
watch&lt;/code&gt; running in one window and &lt;code&gt;jekyll --auto --server&lt;/code&gt; in another,
the site is generated into &lt;code&gt;_site&lt;/code&gt; and I can commit and push the
changes directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all this seems to work pretty nicely, and Jekyll really
scratches some fundamental itch for me. I get to code and tweak, which
is all I really need right now, now that I&amp;rsquo;ve no time or need for
programming professionally, at least not right now. In a way it&amp;rsquo;s
pretty liberating, since I can totally get my hack on without getting
brainburn from too much time spent staring at my code. Expect more of
that then, in this space, along with other stuff. As I said in the
beginning, I&amp;rsquo;m gonna play pretty fast and loose here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to check out the code and source in full, take a look at
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ilkka/ilkka.github.com/tree/source&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; branch in
GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll
be posting about new developments in this front as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>